Welcome to this introductory MATLAB course.
My name is Phil Parisi and I will be your guide.
MATLAB is a versatile programming language developed by MathWorks, and it is widely used by scientists, engineers,
researchers, and really anyone looking to get involved with numerical computing.
This series is made for absolute beginners, no previous programming experience is necessary.
We will learn how to use the MATLAB IDE, what data types and data structures are, how we can manipulate data and perform mathematic operations on it.
And lastly, we'll wrap up with some data visualization tools for you to create plots and graphs of your data.
We conclude with a project for you to solve, where we take data from a CSV file and use it to calculate and plot a path of a robot as it moves through 2D space.
And of course, I will walk you through the solution to make sure your learning comes full circle.
I'm glad you are here, and I look forward to your development throughout the series.
We need to start at the beginning with the MATLAB IDE, or integrated development environment.
MATLAB itself is just the language.
It's the words we type on the screen known as syntax.
The IDE is a piece of software built around the code that offers us many features such as adding new files and scripts,
opening existing files, changing the layout of what we see on the screen.
We can modify the preferences such as the colors and the size of the text we see.
All these features are built in to this IDE to make your life easier.
The IDE is extremely modular.
We can drag and adjust the sizes of each of these boxes.
We can even hide the top toolbar if we want, and come back by clicking one of the buttons up top and repinning it.
And you can even delete entire sections if you want to by clicking the drop downs and close.
You can always go back to the default by selecting layout and then default to get back to the home screen.
Let's start using the command window to do basic mathematics.
Be sure you click in the command window to activate it, and then you can start to enter simple mathematic expressions and hit enter to execute the command.
You'll see that the answer comes out as 4.
We can do 12 divided by 5, or even 4 squared.
You'll see we already created our first variable, ants, which holds the value currently of 16.
It appears over in our workspace, and ants is short for answer.
Now ants is a variable, and variables hold a value, in this case 16, and they all have a name, in this case
ants.
Instead of typing just the raw values, we can actually create variables in MATLAB and use those to add together.
Here I'm calling x equals 7, then y equals 10, and we can add x plus y together to get our new answer of 17.
Now we have three variables over in our workspace, and these variables they help us by providing names for the data that we work with.
Not all data is created the same though, and we need to be conscious of the types of data that we're using.
We can use the whose command, and MATLAB will tell us what the class or the data type of the variable is.
And here we see that our ants, x, and y are all doubles.
Doubles are simply the default numeric MATLAB data type.
They can hold very large and very small numbers.
Before I begin typing, our command window is getting a little bit clogged up right now, and you can clear this using CLC, and it removes the text from the command window.
You'll note that our workspace variables still exist, and we can ask MATLAB for those values by typing the variable name in the command window and hitting enter,
and we still receive out the same value, and we can use these as such.
If you want to clear all the variables in the workspace, you can use the clear vars command and then clc again to start fresh.
In contrast to the double data type, we have an 8-bit integer data type, which stores much, much less data, but also takes up much less storage and memory on our computers.
Here I've defined x as 7.89, and we get the answer right back to us.
And then I've created a variable called y that is a different data type because I've specified that I want this number here stored as an 8 bit
integer.
You might be surprised to see that y holds a value of 8.
That's because integers are only positive and negative whole numbers, so it can't store any decimals.
If I add these two values together, what do you think the answer will be?
Here we get 16.
Also might be unexpected, but this is because we're combining two different data types.
X is a double and y is a 8-bit integer.
MATLAB assumes that we want to get an 8-bit integer out, so even though this value here is 8 and this is 7.89,
MATLAB has created an 8-bit integer to round it to 16.
This goes to show how important it is to pay attention to the data type that each of your variables have.
That's all I'm going to say on numeric data types, because for the most part, using these doubles are fine for many applications.
However, there are three other common data types that you'll encounter in MATLAB.
As we've already seen, we can assign a value to a variable using the equal sign, and this process is called assignment.
We store a single value as a variable, and each of these has a data type.
And these data types affect variable usage and behavior.
Previously, we already encountered the double and the 8-bit integer.
We also have characters, or char for short.
These characters are text, one individual character, like the letter B or the number 9.
We store these by adding a single apostrophe on either side of the value.
Strings are similar to characters, but they're considered to be whole words, an entire entity.
Lastly, we have Booleans, which we will see more of later in the course.
These can only store true or false, which is the equivalent of a 1 or 0.
Instead of running each line one by one in the command window, let's create a script.
Click new in the toolbar, then script.
We can save this file using control S.
I'm going to call mine theory data type dot m.
All MATLAB file names should end in dot m because that's the dot MATLAB file type.
I've copied some text into the script, and you'll notice that we can add many lines without actually executing or running anything.
Let me walk through this line by line.
We saw CLC earlier, which clears the command window.
Clear Vars, then clears anything from the workspace.
And format compact makes sure we're not using a lot of whitespace padding in the command window when we output information.
These are each an expression or a command, and I'm separating them each by a comma, so MATLAB knows to run them separately.
Right here is a comment.
Comments are not run by MATLAB, and you can create a comment by simply adding a percent sign.
Anything that follows a percent sign is not run by MATLAB.
Down here, I'm defining X and Y with four different data types, and we're going to add them together to see the behavior that each of these data types takes.
In lines 5 and 6, I'm using the double data type, which is MATLAB's default numeric data type.
This is an expression where we have a variable, a value, and an operator.
And we can separate expressions, as we saw up here, with either commas or semicolons.
If we add a semicolon, we remove and we suppress any output that would be sent to the command window.
Thus line 5 has two expressions but no outputs, whereas line 6 has one expression, and this will be outputted because we have no semicolon.
In line 8, I'm using the 8-bit integer data type, and we're still adding the same numbers together, 1 and 3.2,
but we'll have a different answer from above, adding the doubles together, because this is cast as an integer and not as a double.
In lines 11 and 12, we're looking at what happens when we add strings together.
I've purposefully modified this to look a little bit wonky.
I added all this white space between the expression and the expression separator.
I did this on purpose to show that MATLAB does not care how much white space you add.
In fact, in line 12, I've completely removed all the white space, and this will still run fine.
It's up to you as a programmer to make your code readable, and thus why all these other lines have nice spacing, a little bit of distance between variables,
operators, and values.
In lines 14 and 15, I'm using the character data type, and we're going to see what happens when we add a character of 1 and b together.
When we run a script like this, MATLAB will go through and run each line sequentially, one after the other.
And then any outputs will be sent to the command window, and we'll be left with variables in our workspace.
There's two ways to run these programs.
You can select the run button up in the editor toolbar, or you can do control and enter.
Once we run this, you can see all of the variables are now in our workspace.
Let's make the command window larger so we can take a look at our outputs.
When we added the two doubles together, we got the value of 4.2.
We added those same values together as integers, and unsurprisingly, we got the rounded answer of just 4, which is an integer.
Adding the string together gives us a funny answer, 13.2.
Because if we put these two values side by side, we get 13.2 like this.
And lastly, when we add the two characters together, we get something completely unexpected, 147.
This is because characters behave very differently than strings and from any numeric data types.
Characters utilize ASCII values, which is beyond the scope of this course, but just know that each data type takes very different behaviors,
and it's important for you to be a conscious programmer and know which data type your data has.
A final note when developing scripts: it's good to keep your current folder with the.m file you're working with visible.
MATLAB also likes to create these autosave files.
It's just in case your program crashes and you have a backup.
Any file in the current folder is going to be usable by any scripts that you have open in the editor.
Keep this in mind when you start pulling data from Excel files or outputting files.
Everything should be in your current folder for
ease. That wraps up our introduction, and I encourage you to play around in the MATLAB IDE.
Become comfortable executing commands in the command window, creating, saving, and opening scripts, as well as defining variables with different data types.
One step up from data types are data structures.
These structures form the core of MATLAB.
In fact, the name MATLAB is actually an abbreviation of matrix laboratory, which emphasizes how important the matrix data structure really is.
Let's take a closer look at the robot data CSV that we'll be using to plot our robot's 2D
path. We have three columns, dx, dy, and confidence, and thus each row pertains to how much the robot has moved in the X position,
moved in the Y position, and then overall confidence of how much we can trust this measurement.
So far, we've only learned how to handle each of these individual values by making them into a variable.
And the question is
how do we begin to handle these groups and sequences of values?
The answer data structures.
Previously, we've learned about data types, which is when we assign a single value to a variable.
However, it becomes increasingly more useful to be able to store an entire group of values as a single variable, and we do this using a data structure.
Here, each value is considered an element of the data structure.
Our first structure is the vector.
Vectors are a 1D, one-dimensional sequence of same data type values.
We use brackets with each element separated by a comma.
Important note here: vectors are a subset of the array data structure.
Here are a few examples.
We have a character array, which is a 1 by 3 vector, with a, b, and c separated by commas and enclosed in brackets.
The shorthand for character arrays doesn't actually need any brackets or commas, and you can put them all together, as I have the first letters of the alphabet
in that 1x16 vector.
A string array, such as names, just contains two strings, and then the double array z data has three values in it, but those are each separated by a semicolon,
which indicates a new row.
And this actually gives us a 3 by 1 vector.
The row separation makes more sense when we talk about matrices.
We're still storing a group of values as a variable, and a matrix is a two-dimensional group of same data type values.
We're still using brackets, each element is still separated by a comma, but now we have rows separated by semicolons.
Matrices are also a type of array, and all vectors are matrices.
Here's a good example.
This double array here, M1, it's got three values in each row, 1.2, 3.9, and 0 in the first row,
semicolon, 4, 2, and 5 in the second row. And we call this a 2 by 3 matrix.
We now have to talk about the super data structure of vectors and matrices, which is the array.
We can have one-dimensional arrays, which we call vectors.
These take the shape of 1 by n or n by 1.
There's two-dimensional arrays, which we call matrices, and these have the shape of m by n.
And lastly we have multidimensional arrays, these are the four-dimensional, ten-dimensional arrays that are beyond the scope of this course.
Here is a good visual tool.
Arrays are the overarching data structure.
Within that we have the matrix.
Negative 7509 is a two by two matrix.
And then within matrices are vectors.
And vectors can either be horizontal, in the one by two here, the 1.2 and 3, or vertical, which is the negative 7,
semicolon, and 9.
This will all make a lot more sense once we start using arrays in the MATLAB IDE.
On your system, create a theory datastructure.m file and follow along, typing in each command and expression as we go.
When we talk about data structures, we define n to be the number of columns and m to be the number of rows.
Vectors are these one-dimensional arrays, one by n if they're horizontal, m by one if they're vertical.
And by this we physically mean if the values are spanning from left to right or from up to down.
Matrices are these two-dimensional arrays, and they are m by n, and visually they look like rectangles.
We can create data structures with brackets on either side, commas separating each element, and semicolon separating each row.
We can also use some operators like the semicolon or functions like linspace to create arrays and structures for us.
Let's take a look at some one-dimensional arrays, which we call vectors.
Here I've defined cities and core values.
Control enter to run, and you see that we get out a 1 by 2 string array here in cities, and then core values just outputs as you might expect.
I'm adding a semicolon to suppress the output.
This variable in array is created using the colon operator.
The colon operator works as such.
It'll take the first value, go to the end value, and skip automatically by ones.
That's the default, so we could write this negative 5 by ones to 5, and we get the same answer out.
You can also adjust this to be any value in the middle, to be skipping by twos from negative 5 to 5.
Another easy way to create arrays is going to be using the lens space function.
Now, first I've defined a to be zero and b to be 45 five.
I'm inputting these here as two arguments to the linspace function.
And then I'm asking for the number of values used between zero and 45 five to be 30.
And if we run this, the yards to sensor array will now be outputted.
It has 30 values because we specified the number to be 30, and they're evenly spaced from 45.5 back to 0.
Moving to two-dimensional arrays or matrices, we have a 2D array defined here, again brackets,
commas, and the semicolon to separate the two rows in the two by three matrix.
And then an alternative way to define this is by using a second line, because this better visually represents how these numbers are organized.
And if we run this, we'll see that they create the exact same data structure.
And by structure, we literally mean the structure that these numbers are organized in.
Here are the two rows, and then we have the three columns.
There do exist other functions such as the magic numbers function and the rand function.
The magic function gives us a 3x3 matrix of what appears to be random integers, and then the random nums here using the rand
with arguments 4 and 1 gives us a four by one matrix.
We don't always have to manually define the data that we work with.
Sometimes we end up with data that we need to load in, such as an Excel file or a CSV file.
We have two common functions we can use to load in data.
One is the read matrix, and the other is the read table.
We haven't learned about tables yet, but we have learned about matrices, so we're going to use the read matrix function and pass the argument of our CSV file,
robot data, and then save that to a data variable.
When we do that, we can go into our workspace and double-click on the data variable to see the data that exists.
Double clicking on the variables in your workspace is a great way to preview the data before using it.
Now that we have all these numbers stored in a data structure, it's very useful to start indexing them.
And by that we mean accessing values, changing things, modifying things, the general manipulation of our data.
MATLAB uses one indexing, which means the first element in a array or matrix or vector is considered to be in the first position,
the first index.
This is in contrast to other languages that'll often call this the zeroth position, but that's not the case here.
Sally is in first, Kino is second, and Hobby is third.
When we have two-dimensional arrays, we'll separate the index values we're looking for by a comma and provide the row number first with the column number second.
We can also take advantage of the end keyword.
Let's see this in practice.
B is defined as 50 equally spaced values between negative 20 and 40 using the linspace function.
The first value of b will pull out right here using the index of 1.
We put the index between parentheses like this.
I'm also asking for the last value of b by using the end keyword.
This is the same as calling the length function of b, which will give us the total number of elements of b, and then using that as our index.
Length of b and end will give us the same index.
And then finally, I'm calling the indices 2, 3, 4, and 5, because if we recall, we can make arrays like this,
and then we can use this new outputted array as the set of indices we want to get out of b.
if we run this, we'll get the first element, which is negative 20.
For the first output, we'll get the last element, which is 40.
We'll get the same answer because length of b just gives us the total number of elements in B, which is 50.
And then when we ask for two through five elements of B, we get this array out.
Slicing is when we take a part of an existing array like B, and we take items out of it and store it into a new variable,
Here I'm asking for the fourth, fifth, sixth, seventh, eight, nine, ten indices from B to store in part of B.
Here, part of B contains those values as desired.
We can delete items in an array by calling the indices of the items we want to delete and replacing them with just an empty array.
I'm printing out the length of B, which should be 50.
Then I'm going to remove the starting from 2 from the end, 1 from the end, and the end index.
I'm going to set these equal to nothing, which will remove them from the array.
And then I'm going to call the length of B again, and we'll see that the size has changed.
Here we go from B being 50 elements to B being 47 elements.
Lastly, we can replace or update values.
Here you need to call the specific indices that you want to replace, the first, second, third, fourth, and fifth.
And I'm going to replace them with equally spaced values, five of those equally spaced values, between negative 5 and 0.
And if we run this and we look at the first, second, third, fourth, and fifth, you can see we've got five evenly spaced values from negative 5 to 0.
Two-dimensional arrays have that second argument that we need for accessing the second dimension.
That's that additional index.
We're going to use the data that we already grabbed previously using the read matrix function.
Let's output rows 5, 10, and 15.
How would we do this?
Let's start by defining the number of rows that we want to output, which I'm going to do with 5, colon 5, colon 15, which gives us 5,
10, and 15.
Then we have to specify which columns we want.
I want all the columns, and shorthand we can use just a colon, because the default values on either side of this are 1 and end.
And if we run this, we get these three rows out.
We should check this though and go into our data by double-clicking it and look at row 5 to make sure that looks good.
Here row 5 is 0.14, 0, and 0.98, which matches our first row here.
And then row 10 also looks good, 0.19, 0 and 0.95.
Now let's replace row 1 and columns 1 and 2 with some new data that we have.
What would be the indices that we use here for data?
We know it's the first row,
and then we want the first and second columns.
I'm going to do 1, colon, 2.
If we run this and scroll back up to that first row in data, we'll see that now this element and this element were successfully replaced.
You may have noticed that we have plenty of extra zeros here at the end of our array.
We want to get rid of those.
So let's take a look and see where those values start,
which is at the 51 here, and it goes from 51 to 60.
We can remove those by replacing the 51 to 60 rows and all those columns with an empty array.
And now when we run this, we no longer have those zeros at the very bottom of our array.
A final action we can take here on this data array would be to slice it up so we can isolate dx and dy columns.
Here I'm isolating dx by asking for all the rows and then that first column.
And we can do the same thing for dy by calling all the rows and the second column.
Now in our workspace we have dx and dy, both 50 by one doubles.
Let's take a brief aside and really talk about functions.
We've been using them a lot, things like read matrix and so forth, and they take this general structure.
We have an output,
the assignment operator, the function name, such as read matrix, and then we pass in some arguments separated by commas enclosed within parentheses.
We have access to tons, and I mean thousands of functions, exist in base MATLAB, and that's what we're using right now.
And if you need more for specialized applications, you can look into MATLAB's toolboxes.
If you need help using a function, or don't understand what the arguments are and what the output should be, you should type help and then the function name in the command window.
For example, help readmatrix will provide me the documentation in the command window of how to use this function.
This can be a bit overwhelming to try and read.
You can also type doc and then the function name, readmatrix,
and it's going to open up the official help documentation with examples for you to use.
This is extremely valuable, and I highly recommend you read through this documentation as it will give you more examples and show the applications of that function.
You can also use doc for operators such as the colon, and you'll see how it's used with some examples.
When working with arrays, you'll see these common functions, such as sum, cumulative sum, taking the minimum, and maximum.
Here I'm calculating a new variable called dxcumulative, which comes from the cumulative sum of the dx variable.
dx here is our argument, this is our function name, and this is our output.
The max function can actually give us two outputs, and you have to receive those outputs in an array like this.
Here we'll get the maximum value found within dx, and then the index position where that value is stored.
Here's the maximum value in dx, which is the 35th index, and then we also get out the cumulative sum, which adds up each sequential value in dx to give us dx cumulative.
Be very careful when you begin doing mathematic operations, such as multiplying, adding, and dividing with your arrays.
When you're interacting with scalars, this isn't much of a concern.
Scalars are plain numeric values in linear algebra.
MATLAB always uses order of operations, but you are welcome to add additional parentheses to enforce groupings.
Here I'm doing some modifications to the dx cumulative.
Maybe we need to adjust this by a value of two, take that quantity and multiply it by 100, and then subtract off 10.
I'm just doing this to show you the layers of parentheses that you would need to perform that operation.
Moving on to matrix multiplication.
This is the first type that we're going to encounter, and it follows the rules of linear algebra.
This is the default behavior in MATLAB, otherwise known as the matrix laboratory.
Everything that MATLAB does follows the rules of linear algebra.
And in linear algebra, when you multiply two matrices together, you have to follow this rule.
In the example below, I've defined M1 as a 2x3 matrix and M2 as a 3x1 matrix.
These inner dimensions, this 3 and this 3, also seen as this j and this j, must agree, and the output will be i
by k as shown here.
So we'll get out a 2x1.
Again, this follows the principles of linear algebra, which you should look up on your own time.
Type 2 matrix multiplication is something you will be more familiar with.
Let's say we have five different speed trials.
Each index here relates to a given trial.
Here we did the first trial with 12 minutes as the time elapsed, and 22 kilometers as the distance traveled, and so forth for each of these five trials.
You're tasked with calculating the kilometers per hour, and so you as a clever programmer are going to put the distance in kilometers divided by the quantity of time over 60, which gives us hours.
When you run this, you get the answer out of 64 kilometers per hour.
But wait, why is this only a single scalar value and not a 1x5 vector?
We wanted the kilometers per hour for each of these five different speed trials.
What happened here?
This is a classic instance of us using the default operators in MATLAB, which are based around the principles of linear algebra.
What happened here is we did that type 1 matrix arithmetic, which uses default linear algebra behaviors that we did not want
because we want to do an element-wise operation.
To enforce this, we have to add the dot operator here.
And now if we run this, we get the kilometers per hour for each of those five trials.
You may be wondering why we don't have to add a dot between the time and 60.
And this is because the linear algebra rule for using matrix division is actually the same as element-wise division.
You can do this either way with the dot or not.
We run this and get the same answer.
For more information on this element-wise approach, you can run doc and then the dot operator you want to look at.
Here I'm looking at dot multiplication.
Another example, let's say you want to square the distances that we have set right here.
You can do this two ways.
You can do dist times dist, and again, you need to add the element-wise operator here, or you can use the squared operator with just dist,
but you need to use the dot square operator as such.
This tends to be a confusing topic for new programmers in MATLAB.
Please, please, please re-watch this section if you need to.
That concludes our in-depth discussion of data structures.
Behind the scenes, MATLAB stores nearly everything as a matrix.
Even the simple value of 7 will be stored as a one by one matrix of doubles.
If you are ever unsure the data type or data structure you're working with, be sure to run whose in the command window.
Now that we understand how data types and data structures work, how to index through our arrays, and how to perform mathematical operations,
we can begin visualizing the results.
I find MATLAB to be one of the easiest languages to use to create clean plots and graphs.
And hopefully, after the next few minutes, you'll feel the same way.
Data visualization in MATLAB is powerful and straightforward.
To get started, create your own.m file.
Mine is called theoryplotting.m.
Whatever you do, do not name yours plot.m because MATLAB has a function called plot and this would create a naming conflict.
Plots or graphs or charts or whatever you want to call them represent data graphically.
On every plot we create, we'll put the dependent variables on the y axis and the independent variables on the x axis.
When we plot data in MATLAB, we're always plotting series of data points with lines that connect those data points.
Everything is highly customizable.
We'll be able to choose the line style, the marker shapes, and the color of everything else.
If you want to learn more about the plotting functionality, be sure to run docplot in your command window.
You'll notice that I added close all to the header that we normally use.
This will close all the figures we create throughout this exercise.
Our first task is to plot a wave using this equation, y equals a cosine omega t.
We're given some initial parameters, and very importantly, t needs to vary from 0 to 1.
We can use the cosine function, which takes radians as an argument, or we can use the cos d function, which takes degrees.
I've defined the initial parameters here, while noting we need a transformation between f and omega.
T, or time, is defined using the linspace function, and this will keep it as a vector.
Here I've defined y with the same equation as above, and we can note that I used the dot star element wise multiplication.
While not entirely necessary in this situation, it is good to be explicit because t is a vector.
To create a new figure, first we call the figure function, this will create figure one.
Then we add a plot to it, and the first argument goes on the x-axis, and the second argument goes on the y-axis.
Let's run this.
Here is our first plot, but you might notice that it doesn't look very smooth.
This is because MATLAB is plotting data points, and when we defined t, we only used 20 data points.
If we were to increase this to 200 and replot, you'll notice the curve becomes much smoother.
To emphasize this point, I've added a third argument to our plot function.
This character array specifies that I want straight lines between each data point.
I want my data points, the marker, to be a square, and I want them to be the color blue.
Now when we run this and we can make it full screen to get a better look, you can see each of the data points are these squares, and between the data points are the straight lines connecting them.
Inside this figure, there are lots of customization options.
You can click and hold to move the entire graph around.
You can click the home icon in the top right to go back to the base plot.
You can zoom in on a certain area by clicking the plus magnifying glass, then click and drag to create a region to zoom in on.
Then click the home button to return.
You can deselect the zoom by clicking the magnifying glass again, and if you hover over individual points, you'll actually see the X and Y coordinates.
We are missing a few key features like a title, maybe some grid lines, and some axes labels, so let's go add those in.
You can add a title to your plot using the title command with a string or character array as the argument.
Similarly, you have X label and Y label, and then you can put the grid spaces on as well.
I'm also showing you how to change the X limits that we show on the plots as well as the Y limits.
When we initially plot, MATLAB will auto-scale based off of the data that you inputted to it, and you can force your X limits and your Y limits if you want to. Here
is the new plot with our labels on the X axis and Y axes, and then our title bolded up top.
The limits that I selected for X and Y probably aren't appropriate, so we can get rid of those for now.
Here's our nice new graph.
If you want to save this, you can click File, Save As,
and then be sure to save it as either a JPEG or a PNG file if you want to use it as a pure graphic.
You can save it as a.fig if you want to open this later in MATLAB and continue editing the figure in this window.
You may be wanting to change the style of the line or maybe use circles instead of squares.
To do this, check out the doc plot.
If you scroll about halfway down, you'll see all the options for line styles, markers, and color names.
Let's say we want upward pointing triangles that are green and have a dashed line between them.
We'd come back to our code and change this to dash dash upwards and green.
Run this,
and there's our green triangles.
Little bit hard to see, but it gives us the result we're looking for.
We can also keep adding extra arguments.
And what we do is we first call the attribute that we want to change.
Here I'm changing the marker face color and then providing the value that I want to set marker face color to.
This is one of the many ways that you can customize your plots.
You can also change the edge color to be different than the face color.
You can change the size.
Everything is covered in the plot documentation.
The next example will be displaying the minimum value of a function as shown here.
I've defined this as a new section, however, and sections are defined using this double percent sign.
Now that I'm running this new code below, I still want to keep my code up top, but I don't want the figures and outputs to keep displaying every time I run this.
So to just run a section, you use control enter and it will only run lines 34 and below.
If you use the run command button in the editor tab,
that will run the entire.m file or all sections.
We have three things to do.
Let's first plot the function, then determine what the global minimum value is and make that stand out on the plot.
And then I want to output the minimum coordinates professionally, as if this were a report.
Here are the steps and I'll go through them one by one.
We should note that we need to define what our x value will be.
We're looking for the minimum value of this function, but we're only evaluating the function over this range of values.
We also need to ask ourselves what's the number of points that we should use to define our function between.
Usually this can be determined with some pre-analysis of the function, or you can just do it experimentally.
Plot and see if you can find the global minimum.
Here we're defining the y vector.
Note that we have to use the dot xmote notation because x minus 2 is a vector, because x is a vector.
Then we're defining figure 2 right here and we're adding a plot to it.
I have one extra command which is hold on.
Hold on tells this figure to wait a moment because we're going to plot something else below.
This is how you can include multiple plot commands on one figure.
And yes, this means that you can plot two lines, four lines, ten lines, other data points.
Anything you want to do can all go on one figure using this hold on command.
And when you're done plotting, it's good form to use hold off.
I copy and pasted these lines from above, and we should rename them to reflect our current data.
Next, let's determine the minimum value of y.
To do this, we can use the min function, and as we saw earlier, we can extract both that minimum value and also the index where the minimum value occurs.
Then once we have that index saved, we can go into the x vector and pull out that minimum x value that correlates to where the minimum y value is.
Now when we use plot again, because we already have the hold set to on, we can just plot the min x and min y.
These can be vectors here, or they can be individual values.
You just have to provide the same number of points in X and in Y.
This will be a magenta circle, and then I'm setting the face color to magenta, and I'm increasing the marker size to 10.
If we run this, we're getting this display.
We're only plotting, looks like a handful, and in fact, we're only plotting 10 values between negative 10 and 0, and we pulled out this minimum value.
Of course, this minimum value is the correct minimum value of the data points that we selected, but it might not necessarily be showing the global minimum value of this function.
Let's increase the range of values we're plotting with from negative 10 to 10, and let's do a hundred points.
This is a much better graph because we've included a larger range and more values.
Now we can clearly see that we're capturing that global minimum value.
Lastly, we need to print out the minimum value. And there are three common methods to do this.
The first method simply retype the variable name.
The second method uses the display command to display the value stored in this variable.
And lastly is the fprintf function.
This function outputs this string, and wherever there is a percent sign, it grabs the next value here to replace this.
Because we have two percent signs, we're pulling in both values to replace those in this one long string.
To learn more about fprintf, please consult the documentation.
When we run this, we'll see that we get the min y value, which comes from line 64.
Line 65 only displays the raw value, not the variable name.
And lastly, our fprintf statement makes this nice formatted output.
If you're curious, the actual minimum value of the function we're using is x equals 2 and y equals negative 5.
The reason there is a difference between this numerical minimum and the actual analytical minimum is because we're only evaluating this solution on a finite set of points.
If we increase the number of values in our x variable, the analytical minimum and numerical minimum should become closer.
And if we run this, we'll see that we in fact do get out x equals 2 and y equals 5.
We just covered two-dimensional plots.
However, as you can imagine, MATLAB can plot in 3D, it can make pie charts, histograms, meshes, contours.
The possibilities are endless.
But the structure of your code should remain the same.
The main thing that will change is instead of using plot, you'll be using the name of a different function, like scatter or plot3
or contour or whatever graphical tool you're using.
Everything else, defining values, using hold on, putting in titles, these all remain the same.
And thus you can use this framework with different plot types.
That wraps up the basics of data visualization in MATLAB.
But keep in mind this is just the beginning.
We could do an entire course on three-dimensional visualizations, plotting multiple graphs on one figure using subplots.
You could do a fifth-degree polynomial trend line, and actually, MATLAB has an entire toolbox called the curve fitting toolbox to allow you to fit trend lines to your data.
Stay curious, because if you can think it, MATLAB can probably plot it.
Job well done.
You have now completed all of the concepts we're going to cover in this course.
Now we shift our attention to the final project.
I'd like to start with a quote from Johann Wolfgang von Goethe.
In the end, we retain from our studies only that which we practically apply.
This is your opportunity to solidify everything you've learned in this course.
It is now time to put your knowledge to the test.
Download the robotpathproblem.m file, which is seen here.
This is a guided problem set asking you to apply the things you've learned throughout the course so far.
After you import the CSV data, the problem set is broken up into three parts.
Firstly, you'll be cleaning the data and performing actions such as removing excess values, updating certain values, and adding a time dimension.
Then you'll be calculating some average velocities in the X and Y directions.
And lastly, you need to create a professional plot that shows the robot's path.
Along the way, you can see I've added guided comments to lead you through each step.
I have also provided some hints for areas that may be of difficulty.
Note there are some new functions being used.
This is on purpose to challenge you and get you used to looking up MATLAB's documentation for the functions.
The final figure that you create should look something like this.
You'll have your initial position for the robot in green, the blue path all the way until the ending in red.
You should include a title as well as axes labels.
You can add in the legend in the bottom left using the legend command, and finally print out the total time elapsed onto the
graph. At this point, pause the video, download the.m file, and try the problem on your own.
Good luck.
Let's walk through the solution to the robot path problem.
We're given the robot data CSV, and our job is to clean the data, figure out the average velocities and X and Y, and then create a professional plot showing the robot's path.
We start off with the robot data CSV, and let's review what that data looks like by double-clicking the CSV file.
Here we have the differential X, differential Y, and the confidence of those measurements taken by some sensor.
If we scroll to the bottom, we'll see that we have some excess values here that we need to remove.
Additionally, we have some values of very low confidence, so we'll want to remove these rows entirely.
The first thing we do is utilize the read matrix function, and this will pull in the robot data.csv file into whatever the current.m file is that you're using.
Then we need to remove the excess values at the end of the file.
We'll call the rows 51 to 60, all the columns, and replace that with an empty matrix.
We are then told that we're missing the time element of our data, and we need to add this in.
And total 20 seconds have elapsed.
We're going to create a fourth column of the data matrix, and this should be from 0 to 20 seconds.
I'm calling out all the rows and the fourth column to add this to data, and we're going to use the linspace function going from 0 to 20.
We want every single column in our data matrix to have the same number of rows, and thus I'm calling the length of data,
which will give us the current number of rows, and we'll use this to define the number of values between 0 and 20.
Then we have some data to correct.
We're going to replace row 1, columns 1 and 2 with this new matrix of values.
There are two rows of low confidence.
This indicates a bad sensor measurement, so we will throw those out.
We call the indices 27 and 35 here in a matrix,
all the columns, and replace it with an empty matrix.
When we run this, our data is now a 48 by 4 double.
We removed 10 extra rows that were excess zeros, we took out two other rows that were low confidence, and then we added in that fourth column for time.
Next, we are asked to separate the data matrix into four separate variables.
We can do this with slicing.
We specify data and call out all the rows to keep and only the column that we want.
Next, to calculate the average velocities in the x and y dimensions, we should do the dx over dt,
or dy over dt, which is the differential or incremental changes in those variables.
We already have the change in x, which is the dx variable here, but how do we get the change in time?
We can do this using the diff function, which goes through this vector and takes the difference between each pair of corresponding elements.
However, when we take the difference of each of the 48 elements here, we'll only get 47 differences.
When we do element-wise division of two vectors, they need to be of the same length, so that we can divide each element by another.
Thus, we have to specify that we're only going to do one to the n minus one of the dx values.
This ensures that the numerator has 47 values and the denominator has 47 values.
This will give us the vx variable, and if we take the average of the vx variable using the mean function, we end up with vx average.
I'm using the fprintf statement to make a nice output to the command window.
The same process applies for the velocity in the y direction.
After running this, we end up with more variables in our workspace, and we also have our nice outputs of the average velocities in the x and y directions.
The final requirement is creating a plot that shows the cumulative position of the robot in 2D space.
We want to mark the beginning with a green circle and the end with a red square.
The first thing we need to do is to create the x and y cumulative vectors, which we can do with the cumulative sum function.
Next we create a figure one and we plot the x and y cumulative using blue circles.
I'm calling the hold on command because I know I want to plot this green circle and red square next.
I'm plotting the first index of the x and the y variables,
marking them with the appropriate color, and then filling in those markers.
I do the same thing for the last value or the end value, marking them with the appropriate colors and filling them in.
Of course, we always want to add a title, X and Y labels, put on the grid, and then for good form we'll call the hold off that we started right here.
Adding a legend is very straightforward with the legend command.
The order that you plot things will match the order of these arguments.
Hence why the path is the first plot, which was created here, and then we plotted the first value, the start, and then the end,
which will match end.
I'm also giving a location argument and putting it in the southwest so our legend appears at the bottom left of our figure.
As a bonus, we're going to add that final time, the total time elapsed, at a certain position on our plot.
To start, we're going to define a message variable.
This message variable gets used by the text function.
The text function takes a X position, a Y position, and a message and puts it on top of our figure.
The message should read total time 20 seconds.
The string cat function takes a bunch of arguments that are strings and makes them into one single string.
Total time is a normal string, and so is seconds.
We want to include the last value in the time vector as a string as well.
So we're calling timeend and then converting it from a double to a string. So it can be included with these other strings inside the string cat function.
We pass the message to the text command and it will be placed at these coordinates on our plot.
When we run this, we now see our completed professional plot.
You can see the very first value is in green at the bottom, the path continues all the way until the red square.
The total time is displayed at these coordinates, and we have our legend in the bottom left.
Our axes are labeled with a title.
To save this, you can go to File, Save As, and give it a file name.
Once you click save, it should appear in your current folder if that's where you saved it.
Here you can see the nice JPEG file that was created.
Congratulations on completing this course.
I hope you did well in the final project, and it becomes one of the many scripts and programs you will write throughout your programming career.
We have only just begun to scratch the surface of what is possible with MATLAB.
There are a few critical topics we still have yet to cover.
Number one is logical Boolean data types.
These become very useful when we're using comparative operators, like is variable A greater than variable B, or if this matrix is equal to this array.
Number two, if-else statements.
These allow us to take specific actions based on outcomes from earlier in our code.
Number three, for and while loops.
These are essential components for control flow, and they allow you to iteratively and repeatedly run sections of your code.
And there is so, so much left to learn.
We can begin writing our own functions.
We can compute solutions to systems of equations.
We can even do image processing, and with a cover use of a for loop, you can create an animated video of a plot.
And with the dawn of artificial intelligence tools, I'll show you how to use it to teach yourself and even use it to write code for you.
Thank you so much for joining me on this learning journey, and I hope to see you again in the future.